<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-05-31T17:43:24+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Daniel Milenkovic</title><subtitle>Freelance Full Stack Developer &amp; Illustrator. Open for work.</subtitle><author><name>Daniel Milenkovic</name></author><entry><title type="html">Overcoming my fear of failure</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/04/08/fear-of-failure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overcoming my fear of failure" /><published>2022-04-08T08:34:16+02:00</published><updated>2022-04-08T08:34:16+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/04/08/fear-of-failure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2022/04/08/fear-of-failure.html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been drawing for a while now, but I was always a bit scared to get into painting. I knew that’s what I wanted to do, but the fear of failure and being overly critical with myself held me back. So I mostly kept to drawing and using simple color arrangements with line work. The occasional attempt at a more painterly style failed miserably and reinforced my fear of painting. But as I learned to be less critical of myself and more encouraging I realized that failures are as much a part of the process as successes if not more so. Failures are how we learn.</p>

<p>I guess I wasn’t really afraid of failing in itself or creating an ugly painting, but rather afraid how others would judge me. Or to be more accurate of how I imagined others would judge me and thus of how I would judge myself.</p>

<p>Once I became aware of this pattern I could let go of this fear by being kind to myself instead being so critical all the time. I mean if you would see your best friend struggling, you wouldn’t tell him he’s not good enough and a failure. So why do I talk like this to myself? This question helped me become my own best supporter. However it’s not like one sudden realization and everything is “fixed”. It’s an ongoing process, but it each time gets a little easier.</p>

<p>So after a while I finally got the encouragement to get into painting. And what better master to learn from than Leyendecker? I was quite happy with the rough sketch in the beginning, but as I got into the painting stage I quickly got lost. I added a rough underpainting, however I wasn’t happy with how it was going and kept searching for the right brush for hours only to get completely discouraged. As I got almost ready to quit I reminded myself to let go of my expectations and just give it an honest try.</p>

<div class="row two-images">
    <div class="column">
<figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/leyendecker_original.jpg" alt="The original painting by J.C. Leyendecker I used for this master study" />
    <figcaption>The original painting by J.C. Leyendecker I used for this master study</figcaption>
  </figure>
    </div>
    <div class="column">
<figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/leyendecker_sketch.png" alt="Initial sketch" />
    <figcaption>Initial sketch</figcaption>
  </figure>
    </div>
</div>

<p>I realized what I needed wasn’t the right brush but patience and trust into myself. I decided to only use a single basic brush, since the brush doesn’t really matter to be honest (Sinix did an excellent <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-Nt9fa8jZUE">youtube video</a> on that topic). And so I kept on painting and each time I felt stuck or frustrated I changed the negative voice in my head with an encouraging one.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/leyendecker.png" alt="Finished master study" />
    <figcaption>Finished master study</figcaption>
  </figure>

<p>In the end I have to say I am quite happy with how the painting turned out, but more importantly I learned to let go of my fear of painting, which opened a whole new world.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daniel Milenkovic</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="education," /><category term="learning," /><category term="life," /><category term="painting" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have been drawing for a while now, but I was always a bit scared to get into painting. I knew that’s what I wanted to do, but the fear of failure and being overly critical with myself held me back. So I mostly kept to drawing and using simple color arrangements with line work. The occasional attempt at a more painterly style failed miserably and reinforced my fear of painting. But as I learned to be less critical of myself and more encouraging I realized that failures are as much a part of the process as successes if not more so. Failures are how we learn.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creating my own art education: Part II</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/10/12/creating_my_own_art_education_II.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating my own art education: Part II" /><published>2021-10-12T08:34:16+02:00</published><updated>2021-10-12T08:34:16+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/10/12/creating_my_own_art_education_II</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/10/12/creating_my_own_art_education_II.html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks have passed since my last post, which gave me time to consume tons of information. In this post I will use the acquired knowledge to build myself a system for becoming a better artist. I already own a lot of art books and bought many online courses, but for some reason I never stick with one resource for long. I want to work on my own projects rather than spending that time learning. So my goal is to find a way to get a balance between learning and personal projects and figure out a way for structured learning.</p>

<p>From what I have gathered the three essential parts for my art education are knowledge, structure and community. Knowledge in this context means, figuring out what I want and why I want to do it. Knowing this provides the basic foundation for everything else. This is what keeps you on the path during difficult times. Additionally knowing what you want let’s you reverse engineer a path to get there. Structure includes what to learn and when to learn it. This is where courses and art books come in. In the draftsmen podcast, Stan mentions Radiorunner’s <a href="https://imgur.com/gallery/RXJ2nmH">“Curriculum for the Solo Artist”</a>, which gives a solid outline for an art education. And lastly we have community which is the biggest advantage of a traditional art school. Having peers around you to push each other and to give feedback is invaluable. I think this is what has been missing the most in my process so far. Even though I would label myself as an introvert, I still get a ton of motivation by being surrounded by like minded people.</p>

<p>Ok so let me apply what I just wrote to myself:</p>

<p><strong>Knowledge</strong>:</p>

<p>What do I want to do?</p>
<ul>
  <li>I want to be able to draw the images that are stuck in my head.</li>
  <li>I want to bring stories to life with my illustrations.</li>
  <li>I want to pursue drawing full time, while keeping my independence.</li>
  <li>I want to work on personal and on collaborative projects.</li>
  <li>To be more concrete: I want to work on comics, illustrations for books and many other projects like designing skateboard decks.</li>
</ul>

<p>Why do I want to do it?</p>
<ul>
  <li>I feel like art is a way to finally express myself.</li>
  <li>It gives me a sense of fulfilment like nothing else.</li>
  <li>I just feel an urge to draw the images in my head.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Structure</strong></p>

<p>I know from previous experience that I don’t like rigid structures. I have been through university (quite successfully actually), but I didn’t like the process at all. I also tried joining <a href="https://artwod.com/">Art-WOD</a>, whose idea I really like, but the pacing was too fast for me. Knowing myself I need a more intuitive approach with a sense of accountability. For example I am currently into figurative drawing, which is why I’m currently attending a life drawing class and doing the figure drawing course from proko. Depending on my current projects I’ll see which area needs the most improvement. In addition, I also want to start doing master studies. The part that’s currently missing is accountability. One way to solve this would be to go through courses together, which goes hand in hand with community. Another way could be to post regular updates about my learning progress. For example posting weekly updates about my progress and what I have studied. Hm… I think I might actually try this.</p>

<p><strong>Community</strong></p>

<p>This is where I struggle the most. I don’t have any artists in my small circle of friends. So a way to find like minded people could be to find local art classes in my area and look online for communities to join. If you reading this are interested in learning together, feel free to send me an email or connect via instagram.</p>

<p>Side note: Besides the excellent draftsmen podcast, I found the video by Jeff Whats on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KX0MrnzBJ8M">“How to Train to Become a Successful Working Artist”</a> incredibly helpful and inspiring. He has a very honest way explaining the art journey.</p>

<p>After all this text, let me show a current project I am working on right now:</p>
<figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/deck01_small.png" alt="Skateboarding is the Essence, October 2021" />
    <figcaption>Skateboarding is the Essence, October 2021</figcaption>
  </figure>]]></content><author><name>Daniel Milenkovic</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="education," /><category term="learning," /><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few weeks have passed since my last post, which gave me time to consume tons of information. In this post I will use the acquired knowledge to build myself a system for becoming a better artist. I already own a lot of art books and bought many online courses, but for some reason I never stick with one resource for long. I want to work on my own projects rather than spending that time learning. So my goal is to find a way to get a balance between learning and personal projects and figure out a way for structured learning.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creating my own art education: Part I</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/09/19/creating-my-own-art-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creating my own art education: Part I" /><published>2021-09-19T08:34:16+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-19T08:34:16+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/09/19/creating-my-own-art-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/09/19/creating-my-own-art-education.html"><![CDATA[<p>In my last post I wrote about deliberate practice and how I wanted to apply that to drawing panthers. Well during those practice sessions I noticed that I should go even a step further back and practice on my fundamentals. Even though I got a few decent sketches, I wasn’t able to simplify the form into simple boxes while still maintaining a coherent structure. This showed me I should take the fundamentals more seriously. I’ve watched numerous videos talking about the importance of fundamentals, but I haven’t acted on that advice so far.</p>

<p>Reflecting further on this brings me to the conclusion that the  underlying issue isn’t my lack of practice drawing animals or my lack of fundamentals, but rather my overall lack of structured learning. My approach so far has mostly been rather aimless. Watching countless youtube videos without ever really applying the knowledge and starting online courses without finishing them. Basically taking in too much input, so that I couldn’t process it any more. Still I did progress, but I feel there is much more potential If I take this more seriously.</p>

<p>Marshall and Stan did a series on their Draftsmen Podcast, about <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLVeITADsnvo7TKLAkyrfhjJub1oN_Skn0">creating your DIY art school</a>. Based on their information I am going to create a more structured approach to my art journey. I’ll listen to the episodes again, while taking notes this time and document the process on this blog.</p>

<p>Before diving into my art education I want to remind myself of what got me into this in the first place. I remember very fondly how I used to go to second hand bookstores with my father when I was growing up to search for any marvel comics we could find. Comics aren’t a very popular medium in switzerland (except “Lustiges Taschenbuch”, which exists in every household), although it got better with the rise of the MCU. Naturally I started to draw marvel characters and after a while created my own, with the intention to create my own comics one day. The desire to create comics morphed into the desire to create video games and thus started my career as a software engineer.</p>

<p>I’ve added two of the marvel characters I drew back then, based on a book “How to draw the marvel way”. I’ve since lost the book sadly.
The other two drawings were drawn from imagination. I remember wanting to create a comic with this character wearing a gas mask.</p>
<div class="row two-images">
    <div class="column">
        <figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/IMG_20210919_120750-min.jpg" alt="Doctor Doom, ca. 2009" />
    <figcaption>Doctor Doom, ca. 2009</figcaption>
  </figure>
    </div>
    <div class="column">
        <figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/IMG_20210919_120803-min.jpg" alt="I really struggled drawing the eyes, in the end I simply left them blank, ca. 2009" />
    <figcaption>I really struggled drawing the eyes, in the end I simply left them blank, ca. 2009</figcaption>
  </figure>
    </div>
</div>

<div class="row two-images">
    <div class="column">
        <figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/IMG_20210919_120831-min.jpg" alt="A couple of voodoo puppets which I often drew in school (OC), ca. 2009" />
    <figcaption>A couple of voodoo puppets which I often drew in school (OC), ca. 2009</figcaption>
  </figure>
    </div>
    <div class="column">
        <figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/IMG_20210919_120922-min.jpg" alt="'Gasmask Guy' fights a demon (OC), ca. 2009" />
    <figcaption>'Gasmask Guy' fights a demon (OC), ca. 2009</figcaption>
  </figure>
    </div>
</div>

<p>Now many years later my revived passion for art also reignited my passion for comics. Experiencing graphic novels such as The Incal, East of West, Monstress and many more really gave me an appreciation for the depth of the medium. So why did I start this journey? To create new worlds and make stories come alive through my illustrations.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daniel Milenkovic</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="education," /><category term="learning," /><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In my last post I wrote about deliberate practice and how I wanted to apply that to drawing panthers. Well during those practice sessions I noticed that I should go even a step further back and practice on my fundamentals. Even though I got a few decent sketches, I wasn’t able to simplify the form into simple boxes while still maintaining a coherent structure. This showed me I should take the fundamentals more seriously. I’ve watched numerous videos talking about the importance of fundamentals, but I haven’t acted on that advice so far.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deliberate practice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/09/13/deliberate-practice.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deliberate practice" /><published>2021-09-13T12:34:16+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-13T12:34:16+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/09/13/deliberate-practice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/09/13/deliberate-practice.html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently got very frustrated while drawing. The drawing is based on a mental image with the intention to turn it into a fully finished piece. So I’ve already set the expectations quite high, but during the drawing process I felt like I couldn’t meet these expectations. This led to an endless cycle of making changes, being frustrated with these changes and making even more changes. In hindsight it is obvious that I was being too harsh with myself.</p>

<p>I was attempting a drawing containing subjects I have never really drawn before. So why did I expect to get a perfect result on my first try? Of course every drawing has parts that I haven’t really drawn before, but there is a difference in things that are new but similar or completely new. I guess after drawing for years everything gets kinda similar, since the basic shapes are all the same, but I am not there yet.</p>

<p>Being kinder to myself and accepting failure as part of the learning process 
 helps growing as an artist (or practitioner of any kind). Beating yourself up only introduces even more pain. I realize that writing this is easy, but actually acting upon the advice is something completely different. I accept that frustrations will arise in the future. But instead of falling into a downward spiral, I can use the frustration as a guide. It means something is not working as expected and that there is potential for growth.</p>

<p>Understand what is not working and from there try to see how you can solve this problem. In my case the main frustration arose from trying to draw a black panther. I was able to get the basic outline and a simple head through reference, but I just could not make it look lively. I realized that I didn’t really understand the anatomy of the animal and therefore couldn’t turn my shapes into believable forms. I am now stepping back from this drawing and first try to get a better grasp of cat anatomy through deliberate practice. With deliberate practice I simply mean drawing with the intention of learning, rather than focusing on the final product. This means finding good references, do some tutorials and most importantly draw many sketches.</p>

<p>To end this post I want to share a drawing, where I remember the process being similarly painful. It took many hours to finish, even though the idea was clear from the beginning and the overall style is rather simple. In this instance I powered through the process, but got kinda burnt out and didn’t draw for a few weeks afterwards. Nevertheless I am quite happy with the end result.</p>

<figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/snow-min.jpg" alt="I dream of snow, June 2021." />
    <figcaption>I dream of snow, June 2021.</figcaption>
  </figure>]]></content><author><name>Daniel Milenkovic</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="learning," /><category term="drawing," /><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently got very frustrated while drawing. The drawing is based on a mental image with the intention to turn it into a fully finished piece. So I’ve already set the expectations quite high, but during the drawing process I felt like I couldn’t meet these expectations. This led to an endless cycle of making changes, being frustrated with these changes and making even more changes. In hindsight it is obvious that I was being too harsh with myself.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning to draw</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/09/10/learning-to-draw.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning to draw" /><published>2021-09-10T16:34:16+02:00</published><updated>2021-09-10T16:34:16+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/09/10/learning-to-draw</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/09/10/learning-to-draw.html"><![CDATA[<p>I rediscovered my passion for art in the end of 2020. I was quite involved creating art of various kinds in my mid teens, ranging from pencil drawings to 3D. But as life progressed further I put my focus on other things and didn’t really do anything drawing related for over ten years. As 2020 happened, it really forced me as many others to slow down and gave me the opportunity to reevaluate my life.</p>

<p>I noticed how I used to be busy all the time doing stuff I didn’t really want to do, if I was being honest with myself. I was just too distracted to notice it any time sooner. This realization led me to drop a few hobbies, dial back on social activities and question my current career. This of course didn’t happen all at the same time, but rather as a process over a couple of months.</p>

<p>Interestingly as soon as a I let go and gave myself room to breathe old passions started to rise up. I started to feel the urge to start drawing again and hop on a skateboard. Skateboarding was another passion in my teens, which I lost over time. In a sense I feel like I am connecting with my younger self again. Dropping the weight which has accumulated over time. I find it very curious that we are often not even aware over our true needs and thus start adapting external beliefs until we forget who we actually are. Doing things for others approval, instead of doing what is in our own best interest. Recognising this pattern has helped me to take a step back and take life back into my own hands.</p>

<p>Drawing for me is a way to quiet my monkey mind and express myself. It is also a great way for me to accept failure and to grow from it. Since I still consider myself a beginner, it can be frustrating at times, if a drawing is not working out as expected or if something just doesn’t seem to look right. Through this process I realised how brutal I sometimes am with myself and how being kinder to myself has had an effect on my overall well being.</p>

<div class="row two-images">
    <div class="column">
        <figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/figures_early2021.jpg" alt="A few figures from when I started drawing again (ca. december 2020)." />
    <figcaption>A few figures from when I started drawing again (ca. december 2020).</figcaption>
  </figure>
    </div>
    <div class="column">
        <figure class="image">
    <img src="/assets/images/figures_mid2021.jpg" alt="A few figures from september 2021." />
    <figcaption>A few figures from september 2021.</figcaption>
  </figure>
    </div>
</div>

<p>So follow along on my journey into the world of art and the human condition.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daniel Milenkovic</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="learning," /><category term="drawing," /><category term="life" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I rediscovered my passion for art in the end of 2020. I was quite involved creating art of various kinds in my mid teens, ranging from pencil drawings to 3D. But as life progressed further I put my focus on other things and didn’t really do anything drawing related for over ten years. As 2020 happened, it really forced me as many others to slow down and gave me the opportunity to reevaluate my life.]]></summary></entry></feed>